<help_entry>
	<name>dppBranchHeterogeneousGTR</name>
	<succinct>Builds a phylogenetic model assuming branch-specific GTR matrices for aligned nucleotide sequences, the number and parameters of which are described by one or two Dirichlet Process Priors.</succinct>
	<verbose>This function builds a phylogenetic model with one GTR matrix per branch. Both exchangeability parameters and stationary frequencies of the GTR matrices are branch-specific. The number of equilibrium frequencies and exchangeability parameters and their values are specified through Dirichlet Process Priors. There are two versions of this function, depending on whether equilibrium frequencies and exchangeability parameters are sampled separately or jointly (two versions of dppBranchHeterogeneousGTR with different parameters). An extra vector specifies base frequencies at the root. The model overall is non-stationary and therefore non-reversible.
	</verbose>
	<argument>
		<arg_name>data</arg_name>
		<arg_description>An aligned nucleotide data matrix.</arg_description>
	</argument>
		<argument>
		<arg_name>expectedNumberOfStatFreq</arg_name>
		<arg_description>The expected number of clusters of equilibrium frequencies.</arg_description>
	</argument>
	<argument>
		<arg_name>expectedNumberOfExchangeabilities</arg_name>
		<arg_description>The expected number of clusters of exchangeability parameters.</arg_description>
	</argument>
	<argument>
		<arg_name>expectedNumberOfQMatrices</arg_name>
		<arg_description>The expected number of clusters of Q matrices parameters.</arg_description>
	</argument>
	
	<usage>
		<theory>myModel &lt;- dppBranchHeterogeneousGTR(data=D, expectedNumberOfStatFreq=n, expectedNumberOfExchangeabilities=m)</theory>
		<theory>myModel &lt;- dppBranchHeterogeneousGTR(D, n, m)</theory>
		<theory>myModel &lt;- dppBranchHeterogeneousGTR(data=D, expectedNumberOfQMatrices=n)</theory>
		<theory>myModel &lt;- dppBranchHeterogeneousGTR(D, n)</theory>
		<example>D &lt;- read(&quot;example.nex&quot;)</example>
		<example>myModel &lt;- dppBranchHeterogeneousGTR(data=D, expectedNumberOfStatFreq=3, expectedNumberOfExchangeabilities=2)</example>
		<example>myModel &lt;- dppBranchHeterogeneousGTR(data=D, expectedNumberOfQMatrices=4)</example>
	</usage>
	<author>Fredrik Ronquist and Bastien Boussau</author>
	<reference></reference>
</help_entry>



<help_entry>
	<name>dppBranchHeterogeneousGTRCommonExchangeabilities</name>
		<succinct>Builds a phylogenetic model assuming branch-specific GTR equilibrium frequencies for aligned nucleotide sequences, the number and values of which are described by one Dirichlet Process Prior.</succinct>
	<verbose>This function builds a phylogenetic model with one GTR matrix per branch. Exchangeability parameters are shared by all branches. Equilibrium frequencies of the GTR matrices are branch-specific. The number of sets of equilibrium frequencies and their values are specified through a Dirichlet Process Prior. An extra vector specifies base frequencies at the root. The model overall is non-stationary and therefore non-reversible.
	</verbose>
	<argument>
		<arg_name>data</arg_name>
		<arg_description>An aligned nucleotide data matrix.</arg_description>
	</argument>
		<argument>
		<arg_name>expectedNumberOfStatFreq</arg_name>
		<arg_description>The expected number of clusters of equilibrium frequencies.</arg_description>
	</argument>
	<usage>
		<theory>myModel &lt;- dppBranchHeterogeneousGTR(data=D, expectedNumberOfStatFreq=n)</theory>
		<theory>myModel &lt;- dppBranchHeterogeneousGTR(D, n)</theory>
		<example>D &lt;- read(&quot;example.nex&quot;)</example>
		<example>myModel &lt;- dppBranchHeterogeneousGTR(data=D, expectedNumberOfStatFreq=3)</example>
	</usage>
	<author>Fredrik Ronquist and Bastien Boussau</author>
	<reference></reference>
</help_entry>

	
	
<help_entry>
	<name>dppBranchHeterogeneousGTRCommonEquilibriumFrequencies</name>
	<succinct>Builds a phylogenetic model assuming branch-specific GTR exchangeability parameters for aligned nucleotide sequences, the number and values of which are described by one Dirichlet Process Prior.</succinct>
	<verbose>This function builds a phylogenetic model with one GTR matrix per branch. Equilibrium frequencies are shared by all branches. Exchangeability parameters of the GTR matrices are branch-specific. The number of sets of exchangeability parameters and their values are specified through a Dirichlet Process Prior. An extra vector specifies base frequencies at the root. The model overall is non-stationary and therefore non-reversible.
	</verbose>
	<argument>
		<arg_name>data</arg_name>
		<arg_description>An aligned nucleotide data matrix.</arg_description>
	</argument>
	<argument>
		<arg_name>expectedNumberOfExchangeabilities</arg_name>
		<arg_description>The expected number of clusters of exchangeability parameters.</arg_description>
	</argument>
	
	<usage>
		<theory>myModel &lt;- dppBranchHeterogeneousGTR(data=D, expectedNumberOfExchangeabilities=m)</theory>
		<theory>myModel &lt;- dppBranchHeterogeneousGTR(D, m)</theory>
		<example>D &lt;- read(&quot;example.nex&quot;)</example>
		<example>myModel &lt;- dppBranchHeterogeneousGTR(data=D,  expectedNumberOfExchangeabilities=2)</example>
	</usage>
	<author>Fredrik Ronquist and Bastien Boussau</author>
	<reference></reference>
</help_entry>
