<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="lib/help.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<revbayes-help
	xmlns="http://www.revbayes.org/schema/help-entry"
	xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.revbayes.org/schema/help-entry lib/rb-help-entry.xsd"
>
    <distribution-help-entry>

        <name>dnCat</name>

        <title>The Categorical Distribution</title>

        <description>
            <p>
            The categorical distribution, sometimes referred to as the generalized Bernoulli
            distribution. It describes the probability of one of K different outcomes,
            labeled from 1 to K, with each outcome probability separately specified.
            </p>
        </description>
    
        <constructor-help-entry>
        

            <usage>
                <![CDATA[
                 dnCat( Simplex p )
                 ]]> 
            </usage>
        
            <argument>
                <label>p</label>
                <argumentPassingMethod>by-const-reference</argumentPassingMethod>
                <argumentNodeType>any-DAG-node</argumentNodeType>
                <description>Vector of outcome probabilities</description>
                <valueType>Simplex</valueType>
            </argument>

            <returnValue>Dist_categorical, Distribution, RevObject</returnValue>

            <details>
                <!-- Since this section can be lengthy, the text is sectioned with <p> tags -->
                <p>
                    The argument to the constructor is a simplex containing the
                    probabilities of the outcomes. The outcomes are labeled from
                    1 to K, where K is the number of elements in the simplex.
                    Outcome i has probability specified by component i
                    in the simplex.
                </p>
                
                <p>
                    A typical scenario where a categorical variable is used
                    is in the definition of a variable drawn from a mixture.
                    A vector of mixture components is set up first, and then
                    a stochastic variable drawn from a categorical distribution
                    is used as an index in a deterministic assignment that
                    points to a component in the mixture. See example below.
                </p>

            </details>

            <example>
                <![CDATA[
                 # Define a stochastic variable x that is drawn from
                 # a categorical distribution with 4 categories, each
                 # category having the same probability, then examine
                 # the value of x.
                 x ~ dnCat( simplex(1,1,1,1) )
                 x

                 # Draw 10 values from the distribution and place them
                 # in a vector a, then examine a.
                 for ( i in 1:10 ) {
                    a[i] <- x
                    x.redraw()
                 }
                 a
                 
                 # Use x in defining a deterministic variable y taking
                 # on values from a mixture of RealPos values representing
                 # rates from a discretized scaled gamma distribution
                 # with four categories.
                 shape ~ dnExp( 10.0 )
                 rates := fnDiscretizeGamma( shape, shape, 4 )
                 y := rates[x]
                ]]>

            </example>

            <author>Fredrik Ronquist</author>

            <seeAlso>
                <!-- The xslt page will try to auto generate links to the referred help entries, therefore only exact names of help items should be listed here (case sensitive) -->
                <entry>dcat</entry>
                <entry>rcat</entry>
            </seeAlso>


        </constructor-help-entry>
    
    

    </distribution-help-entry>

</revbayes-help>

