<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="lib/help.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<revbayes-help
	xmlns="http://www.revbayes.org/schema/help-entry"
	xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.revbayes.org/schema/help-entry lib/rb-help-entry.xsd"
>
    <distribution-help-entry>

        <name>dnDPP</name>

        <title>The Dirichlet process prior distribution</title>

        <description>
            <p>
            This function returns a Dirichlet process prior (DPP) distribution. 
            </p>
        </description>
    
        <constructor-help-entry>
        

            <usage>
                <![CDATA[
                 dnDPP( RealPos concentration, Distribution__<type> baseDistribution, Natural numElements )
                 ]]> 
            </usage>
        
            <argument>
                <label>concentration</label>
                <argumentPassingMethod>by-const-reference</argumentPassingMethod>
                <argumentNodeType>any-DAG-node</argumentNodeType>
                <description>The concentration parameter of the DPP (can be computed using fnDPPConcFromMean function).</description>
                <valueType>RealPos</valueType>
            </argument>
            <argument>
                <label>baseDistribution</label>
                <argumentPassingMethod>by-const-reference</argumentPassingMethod>
                <argumentNodeType>any-DAG-node</argumentNodeType>
                <description>The DPP base distribution. This also gives the Rev type of the stochastic node created with this distribution.</description>
                <valueType>{Distribution__Real, Distribution__RealPos, Distribution__Natural, Distribution__Integer, Distribution__Probability, or Distribution__Simplex}</valueType>
            </argument>
            <argument>
                <label>numElements</label>
                <argumentPassingMethod>by-value</argumentPassingMethod>
                <argumentNodeType>any-DAG-node</argumentNodeType>
                <description>The number of elements distributed by the DPP.</description>
                <valueType>Natural</valueType>
            </argument>

            <returnValue>Dist_dpp, Distribution__-see types above-[], Distribution, RevObject</returnValue>

            <details>
                <!-- Since this section can be lengthy, the text is sectioned with <p> tags -->
                <p>
                This function constructs a Dirichlet process prior distribution. The DPP is used to model
                mixtures of data. For example, this distribution is used as a prior on lineage-specific
                substitution rates as a model for relaxing the assumption of a strict molecular clock (Heath et al. 2012).
                </p>
                <p>
                In RevBayes this distribution is templated, meaning that it can be used for different types of
                parameters. Thus, depending on the type of the base distribution, the DPP can be a prior on elements 
                with Real, RealPos, Integer, Natural, Probability, or Simplex parameters. 
                The distribution constructor creates a stochastic node that is a vector of N elements of the type listed above,
                were N is the number of elements distributed under the DPP. 
                </p>
                <p>
                The DPP is an infinite mixture model and take 2 parameters: the concentration parameter (a) and 
                the base distribution (G_0). The concentration parameter influences the number of parameter categories
                and the base distribution is the prior distribution from which parameter values for each
                category are drawn. For more information see: Ferguson (1973); Antoniak (1974); Lartillot and Philippe (2004);
                Huelsenbeck et al. (2006); Ané et al. (2007); Huelsenbeck and Suchard (2007); Heath et al. (2012); 
                Heath (2012)
                </p>
            </details>

            <example>
                <![CDATA[
             ## number of DPP elements
             N <- 10
             
             ## prior mean number of categories
             k <- 8
             
             ## concentration parameter of the DPP
             a <- fnDPPConcFromMean(k, N)
             
             ## G_0 distribution
             G_0 = dnExponential(1.0)
             
             ## DPP distribution constructior
             rates ~ dnDPP(a, G_0, N)
                 ]]>

            </example>

            <reference>
				<citation>
					Ané C, Larget B, Baum DA, Smith SD, Rokas A. 2007. Bayesian estimation of concordance among gene trees. Mol Biol Evol. 24: 412–426.
            	</citation>
            </reference>
            <reference>
				<citation>
					Antoniak CE. 1974. Mixtures of Dirichlet processes with applications to non-parametric problems. Ann Stat. 2:1152–1174.
            	</citation>
            </reference>
            <reference>
				<citation>
					Ferguson TS. 1973. A Bayesian analysis of some nonparametric problems. Ann Stat. 1:209–230.
            	</citation>
            </reference>
            <reference>
				<citation>
					Heath TA, Holder MT, Huelsenbeck JP. 2012. A Dirichlet process prior for estimating lineage-specific substitution rates. Mol. Biol. Evol. 29(3):939–955. 
            	</citation>
            </reference>
            <reference>
				<citation>
					Heath TA. 2012. A hierarchical Bayesian model for calibrating estimates of species divergence times. Syst. Biol. 61:793-809.
            	</citation>
            </reference>
            <reference>
				<citation>
					Huelsenbeck JP, Jain S, Frost SWD, Pond SLK. 2006. A Dirichlet process model for detecting positive selection in protein-coding DNA sequences. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 103:6263–6268.
            	</citation>
            </reference>
            <reference>
				<citation>
					Huelsenbeck JP, Suchard M. 2007. A nonparametric method for accommodating and testing across-site rate variation. Syst Biol. 56:975–987.
            	</citation>
            </reference>
            <reference>
				<citation>
					Lartillot N, Philippe H. 2004. A Bayesian mixture model for across-site heterogeneities in the amino-acid replacement process. Mol Biol Evol.21:1095–1109.
				</citation>
            </reference>

            <author>Tracy A. Heath</author>

            <seeAlso>
                <!-- The xslt page will try to auto generate links to the referred help entries, therefore only exact names of help items should be listed here (case sensitive) -->
                <entry>fnDPPConcFromMean</entry>
                <entry>mvDPPAllocateAuxGibbs</entry>
                <entry>mvDPPGibbsConcentration</entry>
                <entry>mvDPPScaleCatAllocateAux</entry>
                <entry>mvDPPScaleCatVals</entry>
            </seeAlso>


        </constructor-help-entry>
    
    

    </distribution-help-entry>

</revbayes-help>

