<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="lib/help.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<revbayes-help
	xmlns="http://www.revbayes.org/schema/help-entry"
	xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.revbayes.org/schema/help-entry lib/rb-help-entry.xsd"
>
    <distribution-help-entry>

        <name>dnPhyloCTMC</name>

        <title>Continuous time Markov chain along a phylogeny.</title>

        <description>
            <p>
            A continuous time Markov model along a given phylogeny.
            </p>
        </description>
    
        <constructor-help-entry>
        

            <usage>
                <![CDATA[
                 dnPhyloCTMC( Tree tree, RateMatrix Q, Simplex rootFrequencies = NULL, RealPos branchRates = 1, RealPos[] siteRates = [  ], Probability pInv = 0, Natural nSites = 10, String type = DNA )
                 ]]> 
            </usage>
        
            <argument>
                <label>tree</label>
                <argumentPassingMethod>by-const-reference</argumentPassingMethod>
                <argumentNodeType>any-DAG-node</argumentNodeType>
                <description>A description of the argument.</description>
                <valueType>Tree</valueType>
            </argument>
            <argument>
                <label>Q</label>
                <argumentPassingMethod>by-const-reference</argumentPassingMethod>
                <argumentNodeType>any-DAG-node</argumentNodeType>
                <description>Either a global instantaneous rate matrix or a vector of branch-wise rate matrices.</description>
                <valueType>RateMatrix or RateMatrix[]</valueType>
            </argument>
            <argument>
                <label>rootFrequencies</label>
                <argumentPassingMethod>by-const-reference</argumentPassingMethod>
                <argumentNodeType>any-DAG-node</argumentNodeType>
                <description>The frequencies of the states at root. If not provided, this will be computed from the rate matrix</description>
                <valueType>Simplex</valueType>
                <defaultValue>NULL</defaultValue>
            </argument>
            <argument>
                <label>branchRates</label>
                <argumentPassingMethod>by-const-reference</argumentPassingMethod>
                <argumentNodeType>any-DAG-node</argumentNodeType>
                <description>A global rate multiplier (branch or clock rate). This can also be per branch rates.</description>
                <valueType>RealPos or RealPos[]</valueType>
                <defaultValue>1</defaultValue>
            </argument>
            <argument>
                <label>siteRates</label>
                <argumentPassingMethod>by-const-reference</argumentPassingMethod>
                <argumentNodeType>any-DAG-node</argumentNodeType>
                <description>The per site rates for the rate variation among sites.</description>
                <valueType>RealPos[]</valueType>
                <defaultValue>[ 1 ]</defaultValue>
            </argument>
            <argument>
                <label>pInv</label>
                <argumentPassingMethod>by-const-reference</argumentPassingMethod>
                <argumentNodeType>any-DAG-node</argumentNodeType>
                <description>The probability of a site being invariant.</description>
                <valueType>Probability</valueType>
                <defaultValue>0</defaultValue>
            </argument>
            <argument>
                <label>nSites</label>
                <argumentPassingMethod>by-value</argumentPassingMethod>
                <argumentNodeType>any-DAG-node</argumentNodeType>
                <description>Number of sites used for simulation and initialization.</description>
                <valueType>Natural</valueType>
                <defaultValue>10</defaultValue>
            </argument>
            <argument>
                <label>type</label>
                <argumentPassingMethod>by-value</argumentPassingMethod>
                <argumentNodeType>any-DAG-node</argumentNodeType>
                <description>What type of character do we use.</description>
                <valueType>String</valueType>
                <option>"DNA"</option>
                <option>"RNA"</option>
                <option>"AA"</option>
                <option>"Pomo"</option>
                <option>"Protein"</option>
                <option>"Standard"</option>
                <defaultValue>DNA</defaultValue>
            </argument>

            <returnValue>Dist_phyloCTMC, Distribution, RevObject</returnValue>

            <details>
                <!-- Since this section can be lengthy, the text is sectioned with <p> tags -->
                <p>
                The dnPhyloCTMC is the central probability distribution in most phylogenetic analyses.
                The dnPhyloCTMC is a branch-wise continuous time Markov process that models the evolution of a character along a branch.
                This specific implementation uses the sum-product (or pruning) algorithm to integrate over the state at the interior nodes.
                </p>
                <p>
                    The dnPhyloCTMC is specified by the instantaneous rate matrix Q. You can provide either a global rate matrix or a vector of rate matrices.
                    If you provide a vector of rate matrices then the number of rates matrices needs to be equal to the number of branches.
                    However, you may use the same rate matric multiple times in the vector.
                    Note that if you use a branch-heterogeneous substitution process then you must provide a vector of root frequencies.
                    Additionally, if you want to model a time-heterogeneous substitution process, then you only need to provide a time-heterogeneous rate matrix.
                    This will be useful for epoch models.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Generally speaking, the rate of evolution is proportional to the branch length. To exactly get the rate of evolution we scale the branch lengths
                    by a rate-multiplier wich is composed off two facters: (1) the branch rate and (2) the site rate.
                    If you want to use a global clock then you should specify the branchRate parameter.
                    If you want to use a relaxed clock then you need to provide a vector of branch-wise rates, which again needs to be of the size equal to the number of branches.
                    If you want to have a different substitution rate for different partitions then you can use the branchRate parameter too.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Very often you want to specify among site rate variation. Here you can provide any vector of per site rate multiplier.
                    However, you should be aware that the model is only identyfiable if the mean rate is equal to 1.
                    Most commonly you will use 4 quantiles of a gamma distribution but you can use any normalized rates vector.
                    Here, we integrate over all possible assignments of a site being in either rate.
                    Additionally, you can specify the probability of a site being invariable which is the same as having another rate
                    with value 0.0.
                </p>
                <p>
                    In RevBayes we always initialize values with a random draw. In order to do so we need to know the number of sites this data matrix should have and the data type.
                    We cannot infer the data type from the rate matrix because, e.g., DNA, RNA and morphological characters could all have 4 possible states.
                    The initialization actually gives you a nice way to simulate data!
                </p>
            </details>

            <example>
                <![CDATA[
                 # read an example tree
                 mytree <- readTrees("data/primates.tree")[1]
                 rateMatrix <- fnJC(4)
                 seq ~ dnPhyloCTMC(tree=myTree, Q=rateMatrix, branchRates=1, nSites=1000, type="DNA")
                 ]]>

            </example>

            <author>Sebastian Hoehna</author>

            <seeAlso>
                <!-- The xslt page will try to auto generate links to the referred help entries, therefore only exact names of help items should be listed here (case sensitive) -->
                <entry>fnGTR</entry>
                <entry>fnJC</entry>
            </seeAlso>


        </constructor-help-entry>
    
    

    </distribution-help-entry>

</revbayes-help>

