<?xml version="1.0"?><?xml-stylesheet href="lib/help.xsl" type="text/xsl"?><revbayes-help    xmlns="http://www.revbayes.org/schema/help-entry"    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"    xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.revbayes.org/schema/help-entry lib/rb-help-entry.xsd">    <function-help-entry>        <name>readCharacterData</name>        <title>Read one or more character matrices</title>                <description>            This function reads the character data contained in Phylip, Fasta, or            Nexus files. It takes as input the path to a file            (if the contents of only a single file is to be read) or the path to a directory            (if all of the Phylip, Fasta, and Nexus files in a directory are to be read).        </description>        <usage>        <![CDATA[		CharacterData[] readCharacterData(String "path")        ]]>        </usage>        <argument>            <label>path</label>            <description>A string that contains the path to a file in Phylip, Fasta,                or Nexus format or the path to a directory that may contain many files in those formats.</description>            <argumentType>fixed</argumentType>            <valueType>String</valueType>        </argument>        <returnType>            A vector of aligned character data matrices        </returnType>        <detail>            The readCharacterData function uses the Nexus Class Library (Lewis and Holder 2012) to read files in the            Nexus format (Maddison, Swofford and Maddison 1996). A file starting with '#NEXUS'            or having the file ending '.nex' will be interpreted as a Nexus file. If the file does not meet any of these            criteria, the content is read to determine whether it might be a Phylip or Fasta file.                    The function works both on individual files and on file directories. Multiple character or data blocks            in a Nexus file will be returned as an array of character matrices. A directory may contain multiple data            files in different format. The function will skip the files that do not appear to be Nexus, Phylip or Fasta            files.        </details>        <example>        <![CDATA[            # Read in character data matrices to a vector            D <- readCharacterData( "data.nex")                        # Check how many matrices were read in            D.size()                        # Extract number of taxa in first matrix            numTaxa <- D[1].ntaxa()        ]]>	</example>        <author>John Huelsenbeck</author>        <reference>            <citation>                Maddison DR, Swofford DL, Maddison WP. 1996. NEXUS: an extensible file format for systematic information. Systematic Biology 46: 590-621.            </citation>            <doi>10.1093/sysbio/46.4.590</doi>        </reference>        <reference>            <citation>                Lewis PO, Holder M. 2012. Nexus Class Library. Version 2.1.            </citation>            <url>                http://ncl.sourceforge.net            </url>        </reference></function-help-entry></revbayes-help>